Guide to the Camille Chautemps papers M1601
Stanford University. Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Camille Chautemps papers
1885-2005
M1601
Stanford University. Department of Special Collections and University Archives
27.0 Linear feet
Chautemps was a French politician and radical socialist leader. He was premier in 1930 and in 1933-34. A member of the first Popular Front cabinet of Socialists and Communists (1936-37) under Leon Blum, he headed the second, less radical, Popular Front cabinet (1937-38). Vice premier of the Vichy government, Chautemps came to the United States in 1940 on a mission and did not return to France. In 1947 he was tried and convicted in absentia for collaborating with the Vichy regime; in 1954 his sentence was voided by the statute of limitations.
Scope and Contents note
The Camille Chautemps papers are broken into eight different series consisting of correspondence, personal diaries, book typescripts, speech transcripts, and collected clippings of Camille Chautemps (1885-1963), who served as President of the Council (Prime Minister) of France three times between 1930 and 1938. The biographical resources of this collection include research materials and preliminary drafts for an unpublished book by his daughter, Antoinette Chautemps Samuels (1940-present). This incomplete work, along with much of Chautemps' own personal writing, attempts to unravel the political decisions leading up to France's capitulation to Germany in 1940 and Chautemps' role in negotiating France's decision. Both father and daughter aim to shed light on the political landscape and considerations that affected the actions of the French government at a critical juncture in the course of World War II. This collection provides a unique perspective into the personal life of Camille Chautemps as well--the correspondence tells of his experience in the war as the father of two sons fighting in the French army and the brother of a victim of the Nazi concentration camps, along with the challenges of living in the US as a disgraced former politician and French expatriate. Photographs and memorabilia of Camille Chautemps' family and the family of his daughter Antoinette and her husband, businessman and politician Howard J. Samuels (1919-1984), are accessible through this collection as well.
Series 1: Personal and political correspondence (mainly between 1940-1960); his correspondence with prominent French and American government officials, including Marechal Petain and Sumner Welles, may be of special interest to researchers.
Series 2: Diary of Chautemps: a record, in French, of his experiences from May 1940-41, leading up to and during the fall of France.
Series 3: Chautemps' publications, manuscripts, and lectures. The typescripts form part of an unpublished book about the fall of France; speeches and lectures are mostly written for US audiences from 1941 onwards and often address post-war Franco-American relations.
Series 4: Biographical and Family History--brief biographies from secondary sources, personal memorabilia, FBI surveillance files covering Chautemps' first decade in US. Official and personal defense documents pertaining to 1947 trial in which Chautemps was tried in absentia by the French court for collaborating with the enemy; also, records of his eventual amnesty in 1954.
This series also contains notes and articles about the Chautemps' family and members' historical involvement in public service. Clippings relating to Juliette Chautemps' career as a concert pianist and her subsequent work as a hat designer have been preserved. The papers and personal memorabilia of Antoinette Chautemps can be found here as well, along with photographs of the Chautemps and Samuels families. Howard Samuels' involvement in politics brought him in contact with three American presidents, all of whom appear in photographs of this collection. Samuels' 1974 NY gubernatorial campaign is documented in this series through a number of newspaper clippings. Antoinette Samuels' close relationship with Sen. Ted Kennedy is also captured in the photographs, clippings, and correspondence of this series.
Series 5: Drafts of Antoinette C. Samuels' biography of her father. Told from Antoinette's perspective; a portrait of Camille Chautemps drawn heavily from his daughter's personal memories of him. Research materials for the biography can be found here as well; much of it was gathered in 1974 during Howard Samuels' campaign for governor of NY, when allegations of anti-semitism were raised against Camille Chautemps. The documents collected by Antoinette in response to this include letters in defense of Chautemps and lists of Jewish refugees whom Chautemps helped.
Series 6: Stavisky Affair. Alexandre Stavisky was a financier whose Ponzi-like embezzlement scheme implicated many high-ranking government officials. His mysterious death, along with the unsolved murder/suicide of Judge Albert Prince the day before he was to have testified in the case, compounded the problem of the prosecution. Close personal and political ties made this the scandal that forced Chautemps' resignation as Prime Minister in 1934. The tendency of the public to associate Chautemps with corruption (the Prosecutor General, Georges Pressard, was also Chautemps' brother-in-law) spurred his efforts to thoroughly document his involvement: official reports, memoranda, and clippings about the case are available here.
Series 7: Relevant Political and Historical Documents. This series incorporates a wide range of materials relating to World War II and the relationship of the Chautemps/Samuels' family to the White House. World War II materials include a copy of Petain's mission to Chautemps in 1940 and copies of letters between Franklin D. Roosevelt and government officials. The Chautemps and Samuels' family had close ties to a number of different administrations: Chautemps saved his invitation to Truman's inauguration, for example, and Howard Samuels kept President Carter's inauguration guide and dinner programs from visits to the White House.
Series 8: Clippings. Chautemps collected many clippings throughout his lifetime, particularly news articles written about or referencing him. He was also interested in clippings that examined or criticized the decisions of French politicians in World War II and kept newspapers celebrating such events as Truman's inauguration.
Access to Collection
Open for research. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Auriol, Vincent, 1884-1966; Blum, Léon, 1872-1950; Bonnet, Georges Étienne, 1889-; Bullitt, William C., 1891-1967; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Castagnez, Jean, 1902-; Chautemps, Camille, 1885-1963; Chevalier, Maurice, 1888-1972; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965; Cornu, André; Cox, E.E. (Edward Eugene), 1880-1952; Daladier, Édouard, 1884-1970; Darlan, Jean Louis Xavier François, 1881-1942; Doumergue, Gaston, 1863-1937; Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970; Guernut, Henri, 1876-1943; Hahn, Reynaldo, 1875-1947; Henry-Haye, G.; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Lamoureux, Lucien, 1888-; Laval, Pierre, 1883-1945; Lemaigre Dubreuil, Jacques, 1894-1955; Maeterlinck, Maurice, 1862-1949; Malliavin, René; Michelson, Charles, 1869-1948; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-; O'Neill, Tip; Pétain, Philippe, 1856-1951; Piot, Jean; Pomaret, Charles Henri, 1897-; Prince, Albert, 1883-1934; Reynaud, Paul, 1878-1966; Romains, Jules, 1885-1972; Roosevelt, Franklin D., Mrs.; Rougier, Louis Auguste Paul, 1889-; Schuman, Robert, 1886-1963; Senator Edward M. Kennedy.; Stavisky, Alexandre, 1886-1934; Thibaud, Jacques, 1880-1953; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Welles, Sumner, 1892-; Weygand, Maxime, 1867-1965
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Family Correspondence
    - Chautemps, Felix: Letter to his wife, Oct. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chautemps, Felix: Postcard from front in 1914, Letter reporting his death in 1915 and news clipping (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chautemps, Felix: Reference to funeral of, by M. Bailly in 1915 and 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Lieutenant Abeille: Letter of Mme. Chautemps, 1919, 1929 (?) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bouquet, Edouard: Letter to his son, Jean-Pierre, 5 September 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Chautemps, Pierre: Letters and telegrams relating to detention and death at Belsen, 1941-45 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letter from Jacques Adam, Claude Chautemps, Jacques Chautemps, Jean Chautemps to "Carrefour" publication, RE: Death of Pierre Chautemps and slander of Camille, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Chautemps, Claude: Correspondence with Camille Chautemps & Biographical Information, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Chautemps, Jean: Correspondence with Camille Chautemps, 1940s, 50s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Chautemps, Jean and Claude: Letters from the front, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Chautemps, Jean and Claude: Escape to Spain, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Chautemps, Margot & Yvonne (Camille's sisters): Letters to Camille, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Durand, Andre (father of Juliette Chautemps): Letters to Chautemps family, 1944-45 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters from C. Chautemps to: Chautemps, Nicole, Jean, Claude and grandchildren, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Chautemps, Nicole: Correspondence with Camille Chautemps, 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bouquet, Jean Louis: Letters to Camille, 1954-55 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Chautemps, Antoinette: Correspondence with her father, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, documents RE: Jacqueline Chautemps (niece/second cousin of Camille?), 1930s-40s (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letters from family to Camille Chautemps, undated (1940s-1960s) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Caviness nee Bouquet(?), Giselle: Letter to Hubert Outhenin-Chalandre requesting financial help, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letters from Camille Chautemps to Juliette Chautemps, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Camille Chautemps to Juliette Chautemps, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Card from Juliette Chautemps to Camille Chautemps, 1956 (?) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Juliette Chautemps to Camille Chautemps, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Juliette Chautemps to Camille Chautemps, and personal accounts, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Camille Chautemps to Juliette Chautemps, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Letters from various to Juliette Chautemps, dated 1932-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Letters from various to Juliette Chautemps, undated (1940s-1960s) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Incoming and Outgoing Correspondence, Alphabetically by Name
    - Copie de Documents: Correspondence from July/October 1940 (Baudoin, Petain, Henry, Baudier) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Berthet, Robert: Correspondence RE: Potential move to Switzerland, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Blum, Léon: Correspondence with Camille Chautemps and related clippings (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bonnet, Georges: Corresponding with Camille Chautemps, 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cairns, John: Correspondence with Camille Chautemps over his book on Great Britain and Fall of France, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Chautemps, Robert: Correspondence with Camille Chautemps, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Cox, E.E.: Letters from/to Camille Chautemps, 1947-1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Letters from "Diario de Noticias" (Portugal) to Camille Chautemps, 1948-1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Dubois, Andre: Letters from/to Camille Chautemps, 1940s, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Henry-Haye, G.: Letter to Chautemps relaying message from Admiral Darlan, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Kraemer-Raine, Pierre: Letters from/to Camille and Juliette Chautemps, 1947-1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - President LeBrun: Letter from Chautemps, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - LeFevre, Geo(rges?): Letters to Jean and Camille Chautemps, 1949-1952 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Morellet, Charles: Letters from/to Camille Chautemps, 1947-1959 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Letters from Hubert ("Siamois"), Andre (Dubois?), and Outhenin-Chalandre helping Camille Chautemps in exile, 1940s-1950s (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Letters from Hubert ("Siamois"), Andre (Dubois?), and Outhenin-Chalandre helping Camille Chautemps in exile, 1940s-1950s (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Secret" code words used by 'Hubert' in correspondence with Camille Chautemps, 1940s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Pomaret, Charles: Letters to Camille Chautemps and Family, 1947-1978 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Roche, E.: Letters from/to Camille Chautemps, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Rougier, Louis: Letter from/to Camille Chautemps, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Roux, George: Letter from/to Camille Chautemps, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Schuman, Robert: Best wishes from, and note on by Camille Chautemps lamenting lack of political courage! (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Thores, Henry: Correspondence with Camille Chautemps, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Incoming and outgoing Correspondence, by Subject
    - Misc. correspondence with notable people (Maurice Chevalier, Bess Truman) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Telegrams from Camille Chautemps to President Roosevelt and Admiral Leahy, Oct. 23, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Camille Chautemps: Correspondence with Maréchal Pétain, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Camille Chautemps to Maréchal Pétain, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Welles, Sumner: Letters from/to Camille Chautemps, (selection of photocopies), 1937-1946 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Camille Chautemps: Letters to/from President Franklin D. Roosevelt, Sumner Welles, 1941-42 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Camille Chautemps: letter to "Daily News" and "Times Herald," 1942 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Camille Chautemps to Winston Churchill and Anthony Eden, 1941-43 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Letters between Jules Romains and Camille Chautemps, 1941-1947 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Camille Chautemps letters arranging for removal of his name from 'Total Espionage,' a book on Nazi espionage, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Camille Chautemps: Calls for financial help to friends, and replies, 1942-1951 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Letters between Camille Chautemps and Charles Michelson, Re: "Radio-Imperial," 1942-44 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Letter from Camille Chautemps defending himself against "Les Fossoyeurs" book, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Letter from Camille Chautemps defending himself against "Les Fossoyeurs" book, (Pertinax CC copy), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Reynaud accusations against Camille Chautemps, and Chautemps' response, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Letter of support from Maeterlinck (1947); Maeterlinck obituary (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Letters from family and friends to various, in support of Camille Chautemps (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Letter from Camille Chautemps to sister relating difficulty of his situation, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Letter to Camille Chautemps on possibility of returning to France, 1945-1952 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Letters pertaining to Camille Chautemps' amnesty and return to France, 1952-53 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Camille Chautemps: Letter to father-in-law RE: Camille and Juliette's citizenship choices, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Camille Chautemps' relaying of collaboration with Republican Spain pre-WWII, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Misc. letters (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Chronological: 1936-1962
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1936-1943 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, undated (1940s-1960s) (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Letters from various to Camille Chautemps, 1960-1962 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Series II: Diaries
  - Camille Chautemps: Handwritten diary, May 1940-41 (Fall of France, WWII) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Camille Chautemps: Handwritten diary, May 1941-44 (Fall of France, WWII) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The Diary of Camille Chautemps (1940-44), Bound typescript (Box 7, Bound volume 3)
  - Copies of Handwritten Diary, Part I: May 1940-March 1941 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Copies of Handwritten Diary, Part I: March 1940-Oct. 1941 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Copies of Handwritten Diary, Parts I & II: April 1941-Oct. 1941 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Copies of Handwritten Diary, Part II: Oct. 1941 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Copies of Handwritten Diary, Part II: End of 1942-May 1943 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Copies of Handwritten Diary, Part II: June 1943-July 1944 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Fragments of Handwritten Diary, Part I: May 1940 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Fragments from Diary, Part II (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Typescript copy of the Diary of Camille Chautemps, Part I (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Typescript copy of the Diary of Camille Chautemps, Part I (cont'd) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Typescript copy of the Diary of Camille Chautemps, Part I (cont'd) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Typescript copy of the Diary of Camille Chautemps, Part II (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Series III: Publications/Manuscripts/Lectures
  - Book materials
    - Camille Chautemps: Outline of book, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Camille Chautemps: Book draft (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Chapitres 1 & 2: "La vraie cause du drame" and "La France durant la menace" (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Camille Chautemps: Book plan for unpublished work, "The Innocent Republic," 1947 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Camille Chautemps: Extended book plan for "The Innocent Republic," 1947 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Camille Chautemps: Section of unidentified book, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Camille Chautemps: Section of unidentified book, undated (cont'd) (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Camille Chautemps: Section of unidentified book, undated (cont'd) (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Camille Chautemps: Section of unidentified book, undated (cont'd) (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Camille Chautemps: Section of unidentified book, undated (cont'd) (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Camille Chautemps: Annotated section from book/article on him and Reynaud, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Camille Chautemps: Cahiers (drafts for book), undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Camille Chautemps: Cahiers (drafts for book), undated (cont'd) (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Camille Chautemps: Cahiers (drafts for book), undated (cont'd) (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - English translation (by Antoinette) of Chautemps' book: Preface & Chapter 1 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Introduction to book (?) (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Speeches and Lectures
    - Camille Chautemps: Speeches to (US?) audiences, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Speech by Camille Chautemps to Radical Party Congress, October 1927 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Camille Chautemps: Misc. Speeeches and Articles, 1940s (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Camille Chautemps: Speech at Rotary Club, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Camille Chautemps: Speech at Princeton on post-war France, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Federal Bar Association Journal (Dec. 1943): Chautemps speech, pp. 89-90 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Camille Chautemps: Speech at Federal Bar, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Camille Chautemps: Speech at YMHA, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Camille Chautemps: Speech in Washington, D.C., 1943 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Camille Chautemps: Speech in Des Moines, Iowa, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Camille Chautemps: Lecture at Des Moines, Iowa, Bankers' Assoc., 1944 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Camille Chautemps: Lecture at UNC, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Camille Chautemps: Lecture at Har Sinai Center Forum, Baltimore, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Camille Chautemps: Radio Interview on Algerian situation, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Camille Chautemps: Unidentified speech, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Misc. speeches and statements by Camille Chautemps (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Various documents and clippings from US lecture tours, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Various documents and clippings from US lecture tours, 1957 (cont'd) (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Camille Chautemps: Speeches from US lecture tours (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Camille Chautemps: Various clippings and documents from US lecture tours (Box 12)
    - Camille Chautemps: Various clippings and documents from US lecture tours (cont'd) (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Camille Chautemps: Various clippings and documents from US lecture tours (cont'd) (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Speeches, article by Chautemps as Mayor, Depute of Tours for "La Grande Semaine de Tours" (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Clippings from speeches to Radical Party Congress, Oct. 29, 1927 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Chautemps speech honoring 66 d'Infanterie for service in WWI, undated (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Chautemps speech before journalist association, undated (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Articles
    - Articles by Camille Chautemps signed John D. Smith: Nos. 1-32 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Articles by Camille Chautemps signed John D. Smith (1949-1980) (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Articles by Camille Chautemps: Nos. 301-380 (1954-1955) (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Articles by Camille Chautemps: Nos. 381-456 (1955-1957) (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Articles by Camille Chautemps: Nos. 457-500 (1957-1958) (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Articles by Camille Chautemps: Nos. 501-529 (1958) (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Articles by Camille Chautemps: Nos. 530-599 (1958-1959) (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Articles by Camille Chautemps: Nos. 600-663 (1960-1961) (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Articles by Camille Chautemps: Nos. 664-717 (1961-1962) (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Pamphlet on local history of Blois, undated, unknown provenance (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Riom trial: Notes of unknown provenance (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Camille Chautemps: Misc. articles, 1940s (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Camille Chautemps: Article on French foreign policy, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Camille Chautemps: Speech/letter to citizens of Montrichard, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Camille Chautemps: Note on economic issue in France, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Camille Chautemps: "Lettre D'Amerique" article, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Camille Chautemps: Handwritten note, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Camille Chautemps: Note defending himself against "Deposition Bernstein" article, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Camille Chautemps: "Note on eventual nationalization of oil industry," undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - "1st Column" & "Column No. 2:" Articles by Camille Chautemps, undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Camille Chautemps: Notes listing/explaining actions during war, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Chautemps articles on Laval's return to power, 1941-42 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Camille Chautemps: Article on "France under Laval," 1942 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Camille Chautemps: "France face history" article, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Camille Chautemps: Article on collaboration, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 16)